Earlier this week, OpenAI pushed out
GPTO OSS, which was basically them
putting out their most state-of-the-art
model as an openweight model that
anybody can use for free. And today, the
reason they did that became a little
more obvious because, well, we have a
new state-of-the-art model. Today,
August 7th, 2025, was the day they
released GPT5.
The live stream that was promoting and
launching GPT5 was nearly an hour and a
half long. But in this video, I'm going
to break down just the things that I
think most people want to know about
GPT5. And then after that, I'm going to
share some of my thoughts on whether or
not I was underwhelmed, overwhelmed,
properly welmed, and what I wish I would
have saw from this launch. So, let's dig
right in.
First off, GPT5 got a lot smarter. So,
they described GPT3 as like being as
smart as chatting with a high schooler
and GPT4 as smart as chatting with like
a college student. Well, they described
GPT5 as more like chatting with a
helpful friend with PhD level
intelligence. But not only is it like
talking to somebody with a PhD, it's
like talking to somebody with a PhD in
pretty much every area of expertise.
Now it's like talking to an expert, a
legitimate PhD level expert in anything,
any area you need on demand that can
help you with whatever your goals are.
As with every new model release, it
pretty much crushed every benchmark they
put it up against. In the competition
math benchmark here, when it had access
to Python, it scored 100%. when it
wasn't using tools like Python, it still
got a 96.7%.
It beats out all the other models at
Frontier Math. Keep in mind, they're
only comparing it to other OpenAI
models, but I believe it's still the
best benchmarks for any model. On the
Harvard MIT mathematics tournament, when
it had access to Python, scored 100%. In
this Google proof exam here for PhD
level science questions with Python,
scored 89%. Humanity's Last Exam pretty
much top of the pack does great on
coding benchmarks again only comparing
itself against the OpenAI benchmarks.
Enthropic released their Claude Opus 4.1
which was the state-of-the-art coding
model up until GPT5 came out. So to
compare, we can see Opus 4.1 got a 74.5%
on the SWE here where GPT5 got 74.9%.
So slightly beating out even anthropic's
newest coding model. And as we scroll
through the blog post here, we can see
all of these different benchmarks where
GPT5 is pretty much just crushing all of
the older OpenAI models. On this college
level visual problem solving, it got an
84.2%.
Plot Opus, which came out just a day or
two ago, got a 77.1%.
So, even though they're not comparing
their benchmarks with Anthropics
benchmarks, they're even beating out
Anthropic's newest models benchmarks.
Saying all that and showing off all of
those benchmarks. Even OpenAI is
starting to admit that the benchmarks
mean less and less to most people these
days.
Benchmarks, they're exciting numbers,
but we're starting to saturate them.
Like, when you're moving between 98 and
99% in some benchmark, it means you need
something else to really capture how
great the model is. Another thing that
they mentioned in the live stream is
that they're going to go away with
having to pick exactly which model to
use. You know, do I use 40? Do I use 03
to get more thinking? 03 Pro to make it
think even longer. They're going to just
get rid of all of that. It's all going
to be GPT5. And when you give it a
prompt, GPT5 is going to basically
decide how long it needs to think and
the best way to get to the response you
want it to get to. They also mentioned
that this new model is really great at
picking up little nuances. So, if you
give it a really long prompt with a
whole bunch of subtle details, it
actually does a good job at picking up
those subtle details.
You specify a long complicated task with
lots of subtleties in the initial
instructions. It's very good at picking
up on those subtleties. It's also very
good at if it's gone down a wrong path
and actually goes and executes the code
or hears back from you that it was
incorrect. It's very good at
backtracking, too. During the live
stream, they interviewed a handful of
people that got to use GPT5 early, and
pretty much every single one of them
said that they were very impressed by
the speed. So, apparently, it's a
really, really fast model. And the part
that probably most people care about who
are watching this is, well, who's it
available for and when will it be
available? GPT5 is available to all
users. So, whether you're on a free plan
or a paid plan, you're getting it. Plus,
subscribers get a little bit more usage
and pro subscribers get access to GPT5
Pro, a version with extended reasoning
for even more comprehensive and accurate
answers. And they also mentioned on the
live stream that pro users basically get
unlimited access to it. They actually
touched on memory a little bit as well.
And now they're giving it access to both
your Gmail and your Google calendar so
that it can be more of like an assistant
where it can look at your calendar, look
at your emails, and help sort of take
actions and schedule things on your
behalf.
Next week, starting with prousers,
followed by plus team and enterprise
users. This is changing and we're giving
chatbt access to Gmail and Google
calendar. She then went on to show an
example where it looked at her calendar
and gave her a, you know, half hour by
half hour day at a glance of what she
had to do. Also looked at her emails to
see if there was anything that she
needed to take action on and even helped
her pack for, you know, this flight that
she had coming up that it noticed on her
calendar. But again, as of the GPT5
launch date, August 7th, this isn't out
yet. They said it's rolling out next
week. So, this is not a feature that's
going to be rolled into your chat GPT
like immediately. They also talked about
some updates to the voice feature and
now it's going to be available to
everybody. Even free users can use the
voice chat as much as they want.
We're we are bringing our best voice
experience to everyone. Free users can
now chat for hours while paid
subscribers can have nearly unlimited
access and voice is also available in
custom GPT. Plus, subscribers now can
custom tailor the voice experience
exactly to their need. It will follow
your instruction closely.
They went on to say that the voice
feature is a lot more customizable now,
so you can tell it to just answer in one
word, and every single question you ask,
it will just give you a one-word reply.
They also showed off that it was really,
really good at translation. And they did
a demo where they went back and forth,
and it was actually helping him learn a
new language.
Hey Chad, I'm learning Korean. Could you
help me practicing it? Let's say, um,
let's pretend I'm ordering at a cafe.
Now, what should I say in Korean?
Absolutely. I'd be happy to help you
practice. So, if you're at a cafe and
you want to keep it simple, you could
start with something like,
which means, "Hello, I'd like one
Americano, please." And of course, you
can adjust it based on what you want to
order. Let me know if you want to try
out more phrases.
They also mentioned that the personality
is going to be more customizable. It's
going to start in the text version, but
eventually these personalities are going
to roll out on the audio as well. We can
see here from their blog post the
personalities available initially for
text chat and coming later to voice. So
you can have concise and professional,
thoughtful and supportive or a bit
sarcastic. The four initial options,
cynic, robot, listener, and nerd. And
you do have to opt in and you can adjust
them anytime in settings. And they also
mention that they're all designed to
reduce syphy. So, they're not
necessarily going to just be super
agreeable all of the time. They also
showed off a feature that personally I
don't think was really worth showing in
the keynote cuz like kind of who cares,
but you can now change the colors inside
of chat GPT and customize them how you
want. We got to see a handful of demos
during this keynote to show off what
it's capable of. None of these demos
honestly really blew me away. There was
one that I thought was really cool, but
most of them felt like stuff we've been
able to do before. I guess what's
impressive about these is that I think
they were all done with just one shot,
one prompt where we've been able to get
very similar results using sort of
multiple prompts. Now these models are
capable of doing it with just like one
shot. One of the first examples they
gave was getting a breakdown of the
Berni effect and it explained it all.
But then she asked give me an SVG
animation that better explains this
concept and this was the result they got
from it. created this interactive and
engaging demo that I can actually play
with. So I can actually change the air
speed here to see how the lift and the
pressure change accordingly. I can also
tweak the angle of attack to see if my
plane will actually fly or crash.
Another thing that they demoed was that
when you're trying to code something, a
you can tell it to think harder or think
quickly. basically instruct it in your
prompt how much you want it to think and
the harder you tell it to think probably
the more detailed the output's going to
be. But they also mentioned something
pretty cool about the vibe coding
capabilities was that you can go and
open multiple tabs of chat GPT, give it
the exact same prompt of the thing you
want it to code in multiple windows and
it will go and code three or four
variations of it and you just pick the
variation that came out the best for
you. like they vibe coded this French
mouse game which looks a lot like snake
but with a mouse head trying to chase
cheese but other than that it looks
exactly like snake but it also made
another variation here in a separate
window and they did have it code a third
variation but they didn't actually show
the third variation they also showed it
making this really impressive financial
dashboard that was really welldesigned
had great colors when he hovers over the
chart you can actually see that it's got
the numbers in real time as he moves the
mouse around, you can actually see the
expenses in and revenue. A very
beautiful looking dashboard all done
with one prompt. And it took a couple
minutes to generate, but the output was
really, really good. But probably the
most impressive demo from the entire
live stream was this castle game that
they made that is a completely 3D game.
You can see the little like guards
walking around on the castle. They can
rotate in 3D space and get any angle on
it that you want. And I mean, it's got a
lot of fine little details in there.
There's a chat. You can see down in the
bottom right, you've got the various
characters and you can send chat
messages and have conversations with the
characters in the castle. And there's
actually a little gameplay element to it
where there's these little balloons that
fly around and you can actually fire
cannons and try to take down the
balloons. For the game, they actually
handed it over to Greg Brockman to try
to play the game. And you can see that
he's trying to pop the balloons as they
fly around with the cannons from the
castle. I mean, it's a pretty impressive
looking game. I'm assuming they used 3JS
to code it, but they didn't specifically
specify in the demo. They also talked a
bit about safety in this live stream and
how it's designed to minimize
hallucinations. We can see this chart
that they created. I'm guessing lower is
better on this chart because pink is
GPT5 with thinking. Open AAI is 03. And
so yeah, that's the hallucination rate.
So 0.7% versus uh 4.5%. So they're
getting the amount of hallucinations
down by quite a bit. They also mentioned
that they're doing their best to
minimize deception. And to me, it's just
crazy that we even need to think about
the fact that these AI models might try
to deceive people. But they're working
hard to minimize the deception rate on
these models. You can see encoding
deception. GPT5 16.5%
versus 47.4%
in missing image 9.9% versus 86.7%.
I don't totally understand what these
benchmarks mean other than they're
trying to get the models to deceive you
less which yeah that seems like a pretty
important thing. They also mentioned
that the model is going to give you a
response less often that sounds like
sorry I can't help you with that. So, if
you ask it to give you instructions on
how to make fireworks, I believe that
was one of their examples. Instead of
saying, "I'm sorry, I can't help you
with that," it might point you to
ethical legal resources to get help with
that. And it also seems to have a little
bit better understanding of intent. So,
it could kind of tell if your prompt was
intended for malicious use versus an
actual helpful use case, which seems
interesting. I don't that seems like
jailbreaking opportunities for me to
tweak with intent to get what you want
out of it, but I'm no expert on that so
I don't totally know how it works. When
it comes to the API, GPT5 is available
in OpenAI's API starting immediately.
And it comes in three flavors. You've
got GPT5, the, you know, highestend
model. You've got GPT5 mini, which is
like, I guess the middle ground, and
GPT5 Nano, which is the smaller, likely
faster but not quite a smart model. And
then the pricing to use the APIs
reflects, you know, how fast and how
smart the model is. And they seem pretty
on par with most other APIs. So it'll
probably be the new standard for most
people using OpenAI APIs. For those
interested in the API, there is a new
variable called reasoning effort. So you
can tell it how long or how little to
reason. So if you need a very very fast
response for whatever the app is you're
building, you can have a very low
reasoning effort. And if you want it to
be smarter and give a more thoughtout
response, you can give it a higher
reasoning effort. They're also adding a
new verbosity parameter with a low,
medium, high value. So you can actually
tell it whether you want the output to
have a lot of words or a little bit of
words. The context window boosted to
400,000 tokens, which is roughly 300,000
words of input and output. They also
mentioned that they're giving free
access in Cursor for a limited window. I
think they said like a week you can get
in and use GPT5 inside of Cursor and
Cursor is going to default to GPT5 now
when you log in because the founder of
Cursor actually came on the live stream
and said that this is the best coding
model on the market right now. And
that's pretty much the recap of
everything they covered on this GPT5
live stream. Now, they do have some blog
posts here that have some additional
demos that you can play with. They've
got this pixel art tool that you can
play with and, you know, draw pictures.
It looks like a sort of Microsoft Paint,
some sort of typing game, a drum
simulator. They also have some examples
where you can compare a GPT40 response
to GPT5 cuz they claim that this is much
better at writing than the previous
model. So, you can actually see the
difference here. So definitely check out
the blog post over on OpenAI if you want
to see some more demos and if you really
want to dive deeper into like the
benchmarks and things like that. They
also have a separate blog post here on
uh GPT5 for developers. So if you are a
developer that wants to use the API,
there's a lot more information here. It
works in cursor windsurf forcell jet
brains factory lovable gitlab augmented
code github cognition. So it's pretty
much being integrated into all of the
vibe coding tools that are out there.
And yeah, just lots of examples and
things to look at on their website right
now if you want to dive deeper into what
it's capable of. All right, so I have
access to chat GPT5 here. And you will
notice that up at the top they've
removed all the other models. So you
have GPT5, GPT5 thinking, and GPT5 Pro,
which I believe these might only be
available on the pro mode, but they got
rid of all the other models. No more
selecting which model you want. And
there's one prompt I really, really want
to test. Uh, I've been testing it with
all the other models I've been playing
with lately. And that's make a Vampire
Survivors clone. Make it beautiful and
functional. Create it so that I can test
it right inside of Canvas. Let's go
ahead and submit that. It's telling me
it's thinking longer for a better
answer. Planning game development,
coding game with React. Thought for 13
seconds. Now, it's starting to write the
code. All right. So, it spent about 3
minutes or so writing all this code. We
can see it wrote about 565 lines of code
here for this game. Let's go ahead and
try it out. Controls are WD and arrows.
Aim with the mouse. And let's go ahead
and run it. Okay. So, we get a page that
says neon survivors. Okay. Okay. This is
really actually
the best quick single prompt vampire
survivors clone I've seen. It didn't use
any images. It just used kind of shapes,
but I mean, it's clean. It looks really
good. The enemies are coming at a more
rapid rate. I want to see what happens
if I level up here.
We're actually getting different enemy
styles. We're getting bigger red dots
and yellow dots with eyes on it. So, as
it gets deeper and deeper into the game,
we're getting different types of
enemies. And yeah, they're starting to
swarm. This is definitely the best
oneshot vampire survivor clone uh I've
created so far with AI. This is
absolutely
blowing my mind right now. It actually
looks decent, too. Even though it's just
circles, the way they put that like
subtle gradient on the edges of the
circles, and you've got the grid in the
background with like the sort of purple
colors. It all looks really, really
solid. Yay, I finally leveled up. All
right, let's try our orbit blades and
see if it actually adds a new Oh my
gosh, look at that. It actually added a
new weapon. This is all from one prompt.
Now I'm leveling up faster cuz I got
more weapons. Let's add a neon pulse
here. Oh my gosh, this is really good. I
mean, the swarm itself is sort of all
merged into just like one, but you can
see all the level ups actually work and
it looks clean. I'm I'm just really
impressed with this. So, as far as
coding goes, GPD5 is from my final
thoughts on GPT5 and this whole demo
that they gave, and I I do have a few
thoughts on it. I'm personally a bit
underwhelmed by the live stream, but
that might just be because the leap from
GPT3.5
to GPT4 felt so massive. If you remember
the GPT4 demo, they were doing things
where they were drawing out websites on
paper, taking a picture of it, and then
that website was just being built with
code. Things we just never seen before
and didn't even realize large language
models were going to be capable of doing
that quickly. This to me felt like, you
know, pretty good improvements, but not
that massive leap that we saw from 3.5
to 4. It felt more like the leap we saw
from 4 to like the 03 models. But I
might just have really high standards
cuz I am somebody that is watching AI
every day. I'm seeing the marginal
improvements happen on a day-by-day
basis. For the majority of the world,
this may feel like a really, really big
leap. I just feel like I was expecting a
little bit more. I was expecting maybe
additional multimodality functionality
like an improvement maybe in the image
generator that we got in 4. Maybe Sora
being directly built inside of GPT5. So
now you can tell it to prompt images and
prompt videos and have it explain a
complex concept and then once it
explains the complex concept say turn
this into a video to explain it for me
or something like that. I was kind of
expecting like this mind-blowing moment
of like oh my gosh, we've never seen
anything like this before. But I didn't
really feel like we got anything like
that from this live stream. It was more
like cool, it got a lot smarter. It got
a lot faster, can think through things,
and it can do more things with just one
prompt. But like we didn't get that,
hey, let's walk around the room with our
iPhone uh with the camera open and see
all this cool stuff that it can now do
that it didn't used to do. like we
didn't get any of those mindblowing
moments from this live stream. They
showed off their agents, you know, last
month and that was pretty cool. I was
expecting maybe GPT5 to be shown off in
collaboration with the agents and
showing that the agents got way, way
better. And I think that's coming.
That'll probably be an upcoming
announcement that GPT5 is now what's
being used in these agents and the
agents are a lot smarter. But I thought
maybe that would come with the GPT5
announcement and it didn't. I also wish
they would update its ability to sound
more like a source material, right? Like
one thing I like to do with Chad GPT is
feed it content that I've written or
feed it transcripts for my YouTube
videos and say things like, "Help me
write a script that sounds like this."
And inevitably, the script never
actually sounds like my voice. You know,
it likes to put the word boom in there.
Like you do this and then boom, this
happens, right? there's always this like
chat GPT feel to the writing and it
never seems to really mimic my style of
writing. Or if I wanted to pull in a
video transcript from Mr. Beast and say
write in the style of this video and get
like a new script that sounds like a Mr.
Beast video or something and it never
really manages to mimic the style of
writing or voice over or things like
that from other videos. And I would love
to see that come to life because I think
that would make it so much more useful
for people that do a lot of writing and
things like that. I was also excited
when they mentioned that there's some
new memory features, but the memory
features were adding better integration
with Gmail and Google Calendar and not
actually like a lot better memory. I
would love to have seen the memory get
even better and last even longer and
remember conversations from like a year
ago and things like that. I'd also love
to see memory being individual to
projects. So, you've got the projects
folder inside of chatgpt. I would love
it if when I'm in one of these projects
here and I ask it a question, it just
uses the context of my previous chats
within this project for the memory
instead of the memory from my entire
chat GPT account. Like, why can't we
just get a memory inside of a project
that just remembers what's going on in
that project by itself? or how come we
don't have agents yet inside of a
project? Or we can't connect this to
custom tools like Google Drive or
Calendar or Gmail or anything like that
within a project. We can only do it from
like a main new chat out here. These
seem like little upgrades that we should
be getting in chat GPT, but we haven't
got yet. But what it really seems to me
that's going on is that the large
language model community, the companies
that are building these large language
models, the Googles of the world, the
anthropics, and yes, the Open AIs of the
world, they realized that coding sort of
little bespoke apps that help one person
solve a problem they're trying to
overcome in their business is like the
killer use case for large language
models. And they're all just leaning
into that. Like Enthropic leaned into
that a while ago when the success of
Sonnet happened and everybody started
using that for coding. Enthropic
seemingly went let's just focus purely
on our API and coding and that is the
main use case that Enthropic is going to
have. Like Claude doesn't even get a lot
of use on their website. Most of
Claude's use is through the API from
coding tools like Cursor and Windsurf.
And OpenAI seems like they're realizing
this as well. If we want to get the most
possible mass adoption for our tools, we
need to be the best at coding and let's
create models that are amazing at
writing code. Cuz if it can write code,
it could kind of do anything. If it runs
into a problem that it can't figure out
how to solve, it can write code to then
figure out how to solve that problem.
But it's not as useful yet for like the
everyday person who just wants help
offloading email or managing their
calendar or scheduling or things like
that. but it's getting closer and closer
because soon it's going to be able to
write the scripts that do help you with
that thing. So, it's like a nice
stepping stone in that direction. But
overall, the live stream was
interesting. I'm excited to get a new
model. I'm excited to play with it, but
I guess I was just hoping for more with
all the hype we've been getting about
GPT5. I thought we would see more, but
again, hugely impressive. Still really,
really exciting to get new models. I
just don't think this new model is going
to change the game yet for a lot of
people outside of those people that are
using it to write code. And yeah, that's
my thoughts on the GPT5 announcement. I
pretty much covered everything that they
announced. It was an hour and a half
live stream and hopefully this helped
you speedrun all of the big
announcements from the event and some of
the demos that they showed off in the
live stream and now you feel more looped
in on what this whole GPT5 launch was
all about. If you like videos like this,
make sure you like this one. Subscribe
to this channel. I'll make sure more
videos like this show up in your feed.
Every Saturday, I make a news video
where I break down all of the AI news
that I think most people are going to
care about. I also demo a lot of the
tools if they're available to demo so
you can see what they're capable of. And
that video comes out every Saturday. On
this Saturday's video, we'll actually
have an opportunity to spend some time
with GPT5, probably do a few tests with
it. And yeah, again, like and subscribe
if you want to see stuff like that. I
really appreciate you hanging out and
nerding out with me. We're entering a
new era and things seem to be
accelerating very quick. It was an
insane week this week and uh hopefully
I'll see you in the next video. Thanks
again. Appreciate you. Bye-bye. Minimize
hallucinizations.
Hallucinations.
Thank you so much for nerding out with
me today. If you like videos like this,
make sure to give it a thumbs up and
subscribe to this channel. I'll make
sure more videos like this show up in
your YouTube feed. And if you haven't
already, check out futuretools.io where
I share all the coolest AI tools and all
the latest AI news. And there's an
awesome free newsletter. Thanks again.
Really appreciate you. See you in the
next one.